[Groesbeck] A. J. Jennings Company records, Inclusive: 1936-1975, undated, Bulk: 1947-1973, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
[Groesbeck] A. J. Jennings Company records
Inclusive: 1936-1975, undated, Bulk: 1947-1973, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
2003
A. J. Jennings Company, 1920 - 1975
14 document boxes 4 oversize ledgers 1 oversize box
The A. J. Jennings Company records reflect the business management of the store located in Groesbeck, Texas. Items of interest include inventories, invoices, and ledgers documenting the types of materials sold by the store, pricing for the time period represented, and cash flow practices.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Albert Johnson (A. J.) Jennings was born 1861 August 21 in Louisiana and moved to Falls County, Texas, with his family shortly after. Jennings worked several jobs throughout his life including in the railroad, farming, and teaching fields. He was also community and civic minded, holding positions in Falls County such as justice of the peace and tax assessor collector. He established the A. J. Jennings Company in the late 1920s.
The A. J. Jennings Company operated for more than forty years with locations in Kosse, Thornton, Bremond, Franklin, Caldwell, and Groesbeck, Texas. The stores were primarily hardware stores offering goods to the surrounding areas. During the 1940s, the Groesbeck location provided regular service and maintenance to the Limestone County Courthouse in addition to its regular operations. In later years, the store began carrying variety goods such as toys, personal care items, home goods, and office supplies.
Upon the death of A. J. Jennings in 1945, the business was split amongst his heirs and continued operation. Vinnie Holland Jennings, A.J.'s daughter-in-law, operated the Groesbeck location until her death in 1975. The building that housed the store on Navasota street in downtown Groesbeck is currently occupied by the Limestone County Historical Museum.
Scope and Content
A. J. Jennings was the main proprietor of the A. J. Jennings Company until his death in 1945. He oversaw operation of locations in Kosse, Thornton, Bremond, Franklin, Caldwell, and Groesbeck, Texas. This collection is centered on the Groesbeck location and consists of some records created during Jennings’ lifetime, however most of the records are indicative of store activities after his death. The collection is arranged in five series: I. Invoices, II. Inventory, III. Ledgers, IV. Legal, and V. General.
The Invoices series documents the suppliers and types of materials requested by the store from 1947 to 1974. Items were sampled, keeping records from the months of January and September, due to their repetitive nature. Remaining items are representative of business practices during the time. The Inventory series documents the merchandise present in the store from 1944-1974. Inventories turn from General merchandise to separation of Hardware and Variety Goods in 1960.
Ledgers include inventories, cash books, invoices, payroll, and general business ledgers. This series provides the earliest documentation of business practices from 1936 until store closing in 1975. Ledgers range in format from pre-bound accounting type books to spiral type notebooks. The Legal series includes official documents such as contracts and leases as well as government required information on consumer credit, ammunition sales, and retail price ceilings. The General series includes information on employee benefits, correspondence, and a limited number of newsletters.
Arrangement
A partial finding aid existed prior to the current processing. Present arrangement is in five series: I. Invoices, II. Inventory, III. Ledgers, IV. Legal, and V. General.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 2003. Acquired 1979-08-00
Related Resources
Related references
“County Expenditures for December Summarized for Taxpayer Inspection.” Mexia Weekly Herald (Mexia, TX). 1945 January 26. Accessed 2020 April 29.
Find a Grave, Inc. “Albert J. Jennings.” Memorial #63710395. Databases. Accessed 2010 April 28.
Hawkins, Tom. “Limestone County Historical Museum.” Groesbeck Journal, 2015 February 26. Accessed 2020 April 29.
Hawkins, Tom. “Tom’s Topics.” Groesbeck Journal, 2015 February 5. Accessed 2020 April 28.
Index Terms
Subjects
Business enterprises -- Texas.; Hardware stores -- Texas -- Groesbeck.; Variety stores -- Texas -- Groesbeck.
Genres
Account books.
- Invoices, 1947-1974; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The Invoices series is dated 1947-1974 and includes receipts, purchase orders, and other financial records collected in the business process. The series is in chronological order and in good condition.
  - Bills and Receipts, 1947 January (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1947 September (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1951 January (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1951 September (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Inventory, 1944-1974, undated; 2
  The Inventory series is dated 1944-1974 and includes registers of general stock as well as hardware and variety goods. The series is in chronological order and good condition.
  - General, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - General, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - General, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - General, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - General, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - General, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - General, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - General, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - General, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - General, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - General, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - General, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - General, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - General, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - General, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Hardware, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Variety, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - General, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Hardware, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Variety, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Hardware, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Variety, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Hardware, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Variety, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Hardware, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Variety, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Hardware, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Variety, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - General, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - General, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Hardware, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Variety, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Hardware, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Variety, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Hardware, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Variety, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - General, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - General (1 of 4), Undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - General (2 of 4), Undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - General (3 of 4), Undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - General (4 of 4), Undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Ledgers, 1936-1975; 3
  The Ledgers series, dated 1936-1975, includes bound material such as invoices, inventories, payroll, cash books, and general business papers. The series is arranged in chronological order and is in good condition.
  - General, 1936-1942 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Invoices, 1941 (Box 1 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - General, 1943-1945 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Financial, 1943-1946 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - General, 1943-1969 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Payroll, General, 1943-1948 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - General, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Invoices, 1945 (Box 2 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - General, 1945-1947 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Invoices (1 of 3), 1946 (Box 3 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Invoices (2 of 3), 1946 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Invoices (3 of 3), 1946 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Cash Book, 1946-1948 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Merchandise & Bank Checks, 1946-1949 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Invoices (1 of 4), 1948 (Box 4 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Invoices (2 of 4), 1948 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Invoices (3 of 4), 1948 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Invoices (3 of 4), 1948 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - General, 1948-1950 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Cash Book, 1948-1951 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Personal Expenses, A.L. Jennings, 1950-1962 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - General, 1951 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Cash Book, 1952-1953 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - General, 1952-1954 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Merchandise & Bank Checks, 1953-1958 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Cash Book, 1954-1957 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - General, 1954-1955 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - General, 1956-1958 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Cash Book, 1957-1960 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - General, 1958-1961 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Merchandise & Bank Checks, 1959-1967 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Cash Book, 1960-1962 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Cash Book, 1963-1965 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Cash Book, 1965-1968 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Merchandise & Bank Checks, 1967-1969 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Cashbook, 1968-1969 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - General, 1961-1971 (Box 5 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Payroll, Hughes, 1972-1974 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Payroll, Powell, 1972-1974 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Payroll, Dockery, 1973-1975 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Legal, 1942-1972; 4
  The Legal series is dated 1942-1972. Content includes contracts and information issued by the government on ammunition sales and consumer credit and pricing. The series is in chronological order and in good condition.
  - Contracts, Leases, 1942-1950 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Ammunition Purchase Orders & Forms, 1944 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Consumer Credit Regulation Information, 1949-1950 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Retail Price Ceiling Stabilization Regulations, 1951 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Retail Price Ceiling Stabilization Verification, 1951 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Business Census, 1954-1972 (Box 14, Folder 9)
- General, 1942-1951, undated; 5
  The General series, dated 1942-1951, includes general business information such as benefits, correspondence, and newsletters. The series is arranged in chronological order and in good condition.
  - Product Information, Undated (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Employee Benefits, 1942-1971 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Business Correspondence, 1946-1949 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Newsletters, 1951 (Box 14, Folder 13)